

Via Casamassima, 33 70010, Capurso (BA), Italy

T +39 080 4551829 C +39 329 4082680

piero.molino@gmail.com

Profile

Being a curious mind searching for ways to bring together his different cultural interests, I am very fascinated by the interconnections between knowledge, language and learning. I love to search for non-obvious solutions to problems, following a multidisciplinary approach in order to learn new and diverse things and have new experiences. I developed strong technical skills in different fields of artificial intelligence and I am willing to apply them to challenging and interesting problems.

Experience

CTO, QuestionCube, Bari, Italy, 7/2011-Now

Foundation of QuestionCube (http://www.questioncube.com) a startup working on question answering, development of several question answering solutions: Wikiedi, a question answering system over Wikipedia with NLP and semantic technologies (www.wikiedi.it Still in closed Beta); PArisponde, a government semantic search engine over FAQ Open Data (parisponde.questioncube.com available on Apple AppStore and Google Play - Won the special prize of Apps4ltaly); AQPrisponde, a question answering system for help desk operators (www.ask2me.info).

Computational Design, FF3300, Bari, Italy - 3-7/2015

Working on generative design and data visualization on the web.

Research Intern, Yahoo! Lab, Barcelona, Spain - 9-12/2013

Research project about the adoption of semantic models and network-based approaches for community question answering.

Developer, Freelance, Bari, Italy - 2010-Now

Development of No, Birdie, No! (<u>www.kongregate.com/games/Carnefrisca/no-birdie-no</u>), a funny 2D pixel art game for the Edge Create 2012 contest.

Development of FL-Core (<u>octave.sourceforge.net/fl-core/index.html</u>), an open source package for GNU Octave for the development of fuzzy logic based applications. Development of BitBuddies (<u>vimeo.com/17959258</u>), and iOS application for creating pixel art portraits.

Videogame Journalist, Everyeye.it, Bari, Italy - 9/2004-2/2007

Journalist, Head Editor, International Reporter, Director and Video Editor for everyeye.it (Hidedesign). Wrote more than 40 articles and 20 video-articles about video games.

Teaching

Tutor, XYLab, Castrignano de' Greci (LE), Italy - 7/2014

Tutoring and teaching about search engines at XYLab (www.xylab.org), a workshop about new publishing, video making, hacking and network algorithms.

Programming Languages Teaching Assistant, University of Bari – 3/2012-6/2014 Tutoring and teaching the Programing Languages course of Computer Science department of the University of Bari.

Education

5/2015 - PhD in Computer Science, University of Bari - Research topic: Semantics in Question Answering with Learning to Rank

12/2014 - PhD Course on Semantic Technologies. Cognitive Computing – Question Answering Technologies behind IBM Watson

9/2013 - European Summer School on Information Retrieval 2013 in Granada, Spain

7/2013 - Lisbon Machine Learning Summer School 2013 in Lisbon, Portugal

6/2013 - BigDive2 in Turin, Italy (training program to boost the technical skills in big data analysis and visualization, <u>www.bigdive.eu</u>)

8/2012 - Machine Learning Summer School 2012 in Kyoto, Japan

6/2011 - InnovAction Lab Puglia, teaches how to evaluate the innovative potential of an idea and how to present it to private investors and companies (www.innovactionlab.org) 10/2011 - Master Degree in Computer Science, University of Bari - Thesis about a framework for question answering for Italian and English - Score 110/110 cum laude 7/2009 - Bachelor Degree in Computer Science, University of Bari- Thesis about serendipity in recommender systems - Score 110/110 cum laude

Online Courses

Machine Learning (Stanford University Coursera Online Course by Andrew Ng - Score 100% - With Distinction)

Natural Language Processing (Columbia University Coursera Online Course by Michael Collins - Score 103% - With Distinction)

Computing for Data Analysis (John Hopkins University Coursera Online Course by Roger D. Peng - Score 100% With Distinction)

Introduction to Data Science (University of Washington Coursera Online Course by Bill Howe - Score 95% With Distinction)

Social and Economic Networks: Models and Analysis (Columbia University Coursera Online Course by Mattew O. Jackson - Score 91.3% With Distinction)

Web Intelligence and Big Data (Indian Institute of Technology Delhi Coursera Online

Course by Gautam Shroff - Score 90.1% With Distinction)

Publications

On DBLP - www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Molino:Piero.html

Technical Skills

Languages (main) - Java, Python

Languages (some experience) - Javascript, Processing, Objective-C, C#, PHP, R, HTML, CSS, C++, Prolog, SQL, RDF, SPARQL

Software - Lucene, Hadoop, CoreNLP, Numpy, gensim, Scikit-learn, nltk, jQuery, WordNet, Latex, Matlab, Octave, Netbeans, Xcode, Photoshop

Skills - Question Answering, Natural Language Processing, Semantics, Text Mining, Text Analytics, Information Retrieval, Search Engines, Machine Learning, Data Mining, Neural Networks, Artificial Intelligence, Recommender Systems, Ranking, Mobile Application Development, Database Development, Game Development

Languages

Italian (mother tongue), English (fluent), Spanish (basic), French (basic)

Interests and hobbies

Video games and video game development, digital photography, model building, graphic novels, literature and philosophy

I authorise the use of my personal data in compliance with the Italian Legislative Decree no 196/2003